Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00756
Sophia Smith Collection
Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories
2014-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
SSC.MS.00756
188 Gigabytes 188 GB (157 files)
The Women of Rock Oral History Project documents the lives and careers of women in rock who have been underrepresented or omitted from rock journalism and historical scholarship. The project, created and managed by Tanya Pearson, seeks to facilitate a more comprehensive cultural history, by women, for women and gender non-conforming individuals who have historically been silenced or overlooked as a result of their gender.
Biographical / Historical
The Women of Rock Oral History Project began as an independent study project by Tanya Pearson while she was at Smith College. During that time, and since graduating, Pearson has collected the stories of musicians who rose to prominence before the advent of modern web-based tools for documenting their lives and work. This project is ongoing.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes oral histories of women and gender non-conforming rock musicians prominent from the late twentieth century to the present. Interview narrators were chosen by Tanya Pearson. Interviews are available as videorecordings; transcripts will be available after 2025.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
Conditions Governing Access
Several of the oral histories in this series have restrictions on access to the full interview. Please see the notes attached to an individual interview for information about restrictions that apply to it.
Accruals
This collection is comprised of the following accessions, some of which may not have accession records. Accession numbers: 15S-83; 2017-S-0065. Accessions were received on the following dates: 2015-10-14.; 2017.
Women rock musicians; Women musicians; Oral history; Musicians; Feminists; Hard drive; Digital files; Computer media; Arthur, Kat; Bag, Alice; Ballance, Laura; Barber-Way, Mish; Bonham, Tracy; Cafritz, Julie; de Buhr, Alice; Dorsey, Gail Ann; Gonzales, Michelle Cruz; Gordon, Nina, 1967-; Hersh, Kristin; Lunch, Lydia; Pearson, Tanya; Post, Louise; Roessler, Kira; Ross, Cynthia; Samson, JD, 1978-; Schemel, Patty, 1967-; Sparks, Donita; Sumner, Kate; Timony, Mary
- Kat Arthur interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 October 9; Arthur, Kat; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video file)
  Scope and Contents
  In this oral history, Kat Arthur discusses her childhood upbringing in Princeton, NJ, her family of origin, schooling, and teenage years. She details her early musical influences, friendships and social life, and how she decided to move to the Los Angeles to start a band, against her family's wishes. Arthur discusses the LA punk scene, her experience as a front woman within that scene, her careers outside of music, personal struggles and achievements. The interview closes with her thoughts on gender and the category of 'women in rock.'
  Conditions Governing Access
  This interview is available for research without restriction.
  Arthur, Kat
  - Video interview of Kat Arthur
- Alice Bag interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 July 8; Bag, Alice; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history, Alice Bag discusses her upbringing in East L.A., her relationship with her parents and how those early experiences dictated her personality and musical output. She details the burgeoning punk scene in Los Angeles in the 1970s, the formation of The Bags, subsequent success within the scene and appearance in the cult documentary Decline of Western Civilization. She also discusses an influential trip to Nicaragua, her career in teaching, feelings about women's place in rock music, specifically women of color and their place within the historical rock narrative.
  Biographical / Historical
  Singer, musician, author, educator and feminist Alice Bag co-founded pioneering LA punk band, The Bags, one of the first wave of punk bands to form in the mid-1970s. She has remained active in music, performing in bands Castration Squad, Stay at Home Bomb, Cholita!, and has published two memoirs. Bag recorded her first full length album, Alice Bag, on Don Giovanni records in 2016.
  Bag, Alice
  - Video interview of Alice Bag
  - Transcript of interview of Alice Bag
- Laura Ballance interviewed by Kate Sumner, 2015 April 24; Sumner, Kate; Ballance, Laura; 1 oral histories (Video and transcript)
  In this oral history Ballance discusses her childhood, the development of her interest in music, and the creation and history of Superchunk and Merge. Ballance describes her family's supernatural interests and the impact of a traumatic home invasion in Little Rock, Arkansas, in which her mother was raped when Ballance was eight years old. She reflects on the impact of gender and motherhood on her career as a musician and business owner. The interview also covers how living in the South affected the development of her musical career, and the challenge of being a musician with hyperacusis. The interview concludes with Ballance reflecting on her proudest moments.
  Laura Ballance (b. 1968) is a musician and business owner in Durham, North Carolina. She is the bassist in the rock band Superchunk and co-founder, along with Mac McCaughan, of Merge Records. Superchunk began in 1989, and Merge grew up alongside it as a method to release small-scale recordings by Superchunk and other independent/local acts. In 1992, Merge released their first full-length album, Tossing Seeds by Superchunk, and in 2010, released Arcade Fire's The Suburbs, which won the Grammy for Album of the Year in 2011. By 2012, the label had over 450 releases and had established itself as an indie-rock institution. In the summer of 2013, Ballance announced that she would no longer be touring with Superchunk as a result of her worsening hearing issues. She continues to record with the band and runs Merge.
  Ballance, Laura
  - Video interview of Laura Ballance
  - Transcript of interview of Laura Ballance
- Mish Barber-Way interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 October 10; Barber-Way, Mish; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Mish Barber-Way discusses her upbringing in Vancouver, her relationship with her parents, siblings and friends, her experiences as a high school and college student and her involvement in the local music scene. She details the formation of White Lung, her relationship with her bandmates, the band's trajectory to success and her eventual move to the United States. Barber-Way also discusses her musical influences, feminism, sexism, and her experience as a working musician, journalist and writer.
  Mish Barber-Way is a singer, musician, writer and fronts the Candian punk band, White Lung. She is the sex and relationship columnist in the Vancouver newspaper, Westender, and is a writer and reporter for Broadly and Vice. She currently lives in the suburbs of Los Angeles with her husband.
  Barber-Way, Mish
  - Video interview of Mish Barber-Way
- Tracy Bonham interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2017 May 6; Bonham, Tracy; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Tracy Bonham discusses her childhood, upbringing, relationships with her parents and siblings, her early love of music, and her training as violinist and pianist. She details her high school and college years, a move the the east coast to study vocal performance at Berklee College of Music and how she began writing songs on guitar. She discusses her rise to fame with her debut album 'The Burdens of Being Upright,' the music industry, touring, her relationships with her bandmates and songwriting. Bonham talks openly about personal struggles, subsequent musical output, and her most recent project 'Modern Burdens.' The interview closes with her thoughts on ageism, gender, motherhood, and finding an art/ life balance.
  Tracy Bonham is classically trained violinist and pianist and a grammy nominated rock musician. She has recorded five albums and is currently working on 'Modern Burdens,' a collaborative follow up to her debut album 'The Burdens of Being Upright.' She lives in New York with her husband and son.
  Bonham, Tracy
  - Video interview of Tracy Bonham
- Carla Bozulich inteviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2017 Aug 20; Pearson, Tanya; Bozulich, Carla; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  Interview is closed pending receipt of release form.
  Bozulich, Carla
  - Video interview of Carla Bozulich
- Julie Cafritz interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 January 22; Cafritz, Julie; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history, Julie Cafritz details her childhood, relationships with family members, and her upbringing in Washington, D.C. She describes her college career at Brown University, a traumatic event that occurred while she was a student, and the pivotal moment in which she decided to join a band without ever having played a musical instrument. Cafritz recounts notable relationships with bandmates in Pussy Galore, Free Kitten and STP, and candidly discusses musicianship, gender and personal relationships. The interview concludes with Cafritz reflecting on motherhood and work/life balance.
  Julie Cafritz is a guitarist/vocalist who started her career in the seminal garage noise band, Pussy Galore in NYC in the mid-1980s. She went on to form STP and later, Free Kitten, with Kim Gordon of Sonic Youth in the 1990s.
  Cafritz, Julie
  - Video interview of Julie Cafritz
  - Transcript of interview of Julie Cafritz
- Brie (Howard) Darling interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2017 August 24; Darling, Brie (Howard)
  In this oral history, Brie (Howard) Darling discusses her parents, siblings, and her upbringing in California. She details her interest in visual art, an accidental introduction to the drums, her experience as a working musician from a young age, and how she met June and Jean Millington and joined The Svelts as a teenager. Darling details her experience as a working, touring musician, and young mother to her daughter, and the trajectory of her career in the music business during the 1970s and 80s. She discusses notable collaborations, mentors and tours, as well as her work as an actress and cake decorator. The interview closes with her thoughts on the status of women in rock music and current work on the new Fanny album.
  Darling, Brie (Howard)
  - Video interview of Brie (Howard) Darling
- Alice de Buhr interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 October 6; de Buhr, Alice; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Alice de Buhr details growing up a tomboy in Mason City, Iowa, her relationship with her parents, siblings and friends, and her introduction to the drums in second grade. She details her parents divorce, her experience coming out as gay in 1967, subsequent hospitalization, and move to California. De Buhr details her early music career, the formation and eventual success of Fanny, and the events that led to the bands dissolution. She talks openly about her post-Fanny life and career and her feelings about the bands legacy and her place in rock history.
  Alice de Buhr was a founding member and the drummer of Fanny, the first all-woman rock band to release an album on a major label in the U.S. After leaving Fanny in 1973, she spent the next 11 years in the music business; first at an independent distributor of Motown, Mercury and A & M Records. In 1984 she left her position as Local Marketing Coordinator – Southern California A & M Records to pursue interests in the video industry. She currently represents MTI Home Video as a national key accounts representative and owns a small DVD/video distribution company. She resides in Tucson, AZ.
  Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrator until 2032: 1:13:30-1:19:25, 1:21:10-1:21:26. A redacted version of the video is open for research.
  de Buhr, Alice
  - Redacted video interview of Alice de Buhr
    Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrator. This edited version of the video is open for research
- Gail Ann Dorsey interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 July 20; Dorsey, Gail Ann; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Gail Ann Dorsey discusses growing up in Philadelphia, her relationship with her mother and siblings, and her early interest in music and screenwriting. She talks about discovering the bass guitar, auditioning for her first band, her college career as a film major and her eventual move to London and New York to pursue music. She details her experience as an African American woman, bassist and and an artist working within multiple genres. Dorsey talks openly about her relationship with David Bowie, as a member of his band for twenty years, her career as a top session player and solo artist, and her experience with record labels. The interview concludes with her thoughts on the importance of the documentation of women in music and her greatest personal achievement.
  Gail Ann Dorsey is a musician, vocalist, bassist and top session musician, best known for her work with David Bowie, She has recorded three solo albums, and has supported Olivia Newton John, Tears for Fears, Lenny Kravitz, Boy George, Indigo Girls, Gang of Four and Gwen Stefani, among others. Dorsey continues to perform and tour.
  Interview is closed pending receipt of complete release form.
  Dorsey, Gail Ann
  - Video interview of Gail Ann Dorsey
- Michelle Gonzales interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 August 20; Gonzales, Michelle Cruz; 1 oral histories
  In this oral history, Michelle Gonzales discusses her upbringing in Tuolumne, CA., with her mother and brother. She discusses early childhood events, experiences in school and with peers and her introduction to music, via the flute. Gonzales recounts her introduction to punk and the formation of her first band Girl Fight, and later Spitboy. She details the punk scene, her place within it as a young xicana woman, and as a drummer, in a working, touring, hardcore band. Gonzales also talks candidly about Spitboy's breakup, her personal relationships, sexuality, marriage, motherhood the about writing her memoir.
  There are two corrections that the narrator has made to her interview. At 39:31, when she says, "marched up and down Haight Street," it should be Telegraph Avenue. "Paula and Karen" at 45:14 should be Adrienne and Karen.
  Michelle Gonzales is a musician, author and teacher. She played drums and wrote lyrics for three bands during the 1980s and 1990s: Bitch Fight, Spitboy, and Instant Girl. In 2001 and 2003, she earned degrees in English/creative writing from Mills College, where she also minored in ethnic studies. Michelle has published in anthologies, literary journals, and Hip Mama magazine. She teaches English and creative writing at Las Positas College, and lectures at colleges and art spaces around the country. She released her memoir, Spitboy Rule: Tales of a Xicana in a Female Punk Band in 2016. She lives with her husband, son, and their three Mexican dogs in Oakland, California.
  Gonzales, Michelle Cruz
  - Video interview of Michelle Gonzales
- Bibbe Hansen interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 December 31; Hansen, Bibbe; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  Hansen, Bibbe
  - Video interview with Bibbe Hansen
- Kristin Hersh interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2014 December 14; Hersh, Kristin; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history Kristin Hersh describes her childhood in Rhode Island and how her musical inclination was dictated by her long undiagnosed synesthesia. She a traumatic bicycle accident and its effect on her personal life and songwriting. The interview details her work, musical output and role as wife, mother, and rock icon.
  Kristin Hersh (b. 1966) was born in Atlanta and raised in Newport, Rhode Island. She learned guitar from her father and quickly developed her own unique style of playing. She formed Throwing Muses with her stepsister, Tanya Donnelly, and some high school friends in 1981, playing shows with bands like Talking Heads and eventually touring with the Pixies. Hersh continued performing as Throwing Muses until 1997 when she went on to continue her successful solo career. She formed power-rock trio 50 Foot Wave in 2003 and founded CASH Music [Coalition of Artists and Stakeholders], a collection of tools for artists and labels to sell, share, and promote music directly to their fans. In 2010 she released her memoir, Rat Girl, detailing her teenage years in Newport, Rhode Island. Throwing Muses re-formed in 2003 and the original lineup toured the U.S. in 2014.
  Hersh, Kristin
  - Video interview of Kristen Hersh
  - Transcript of interview of Kristen Hersh
- Lydia Lunch interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2014 December 6; Lunch, Lydia; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video and 1 transcript)
  In this oral history, Lydia Lunch details her teenage years in Rochester, New York and her move to New York City as a 14 year-old runaway with aspirations of becoming a spoken word artist. She recounts her early experiences and relationships in New York in the mid 1970s and details her notable musical and artistic projects and significant collaborations. She discusses her motivations, reputation and sexuality as well as her immense output of physical work and her plans for the future.
  Lydia Lunch (b. 1959) moved to New York City from Rochester in her early teens, intent on performing spoken word. She spawned the No Wave movement with her band Teenage Jesus and the Jerks who appeared on the Brian Eno produced No New York compilation and performed in Eight Eyed Spy and Beirut Slump before embarking on a solo career. Lunch has collaborated and performed with countless writers, musicians and artists, most notably: J.G. Thirlwell, Thurston Moore and Sonic Youth, Nick Cave and The Birthday Party, No Trend, Rowland S. Howard, Richard Kern, Exene Cervenka, Henry Rollins, Donita Sparks, Jerry Stahl, Hubert Selby and William S. Burroughs. She was a key player in the Cinema of Transgression movement, acting in a series of short films directed by Richard Kern. She is a critically acclaimed author and tireless spoken word performer, continuing to define underground music, art and literature with her distinct confrontationalist approach.
  Lunch, Lydia
  - Video interview of Lydia Lunch
  - Transcript of interview of Lydia Lunch
- Miss Guy interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 October 28; Miss Guy; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Miss Guy discusses his upbringing in Southern California, his relationship with his parents and siblings, and his experience at school and with his peers. He discusses his early interest in music, fashion, and how these things afforded him the freedom to express himself and overcome his shyness. Guy details his move to New York City in the late 1980s, his introduction to the drag club scene, work as a performer and DJ, the formation of Toilet Boys and their ensuing career, as well as notable shows and collaborations. The interview closes with his thoughts on gender, femininity and being an honorary 'woman of rock.'
  Miss Guy
  - Video interview of Miss Guy
- Phranc interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 September 16; Phranc; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video)
  In this oral history, Phranc discusses her upbringing in Mara Vista, CA, her introduction to the guitar at age 9, knowing that she was a lesbian from a young age, and how she dropped out of high school to pursue art, music, and the pivotal moment she discovered The Women's Center, the lesbian feminist movement and her subsequent activist work. She details her introduction to the Los Angeles punk scene and her involvement in it, and how she transitioned to performing as Phranc. She discusses notable tours, collaborations and her experience with the music industry, as well as her career in the Tupperware industry. She closes with her thoughts on the visibility of women in rock history and musicians who have been particularly important to her.
  Phranc
  - Video interview of Phranc
- Kira Roessler interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 October 7; Roessler, Kira; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history Kira Roessler discusses her childhood, her relationship with her parents and brother, the development of her interest in music, and her involvement in the early punk scene in Los Angeles. Roessler discusses her experiences joining and forming bands and how she came to join Black Flag at the height of their career. She details her time with the band while a college student at UCLA, and her eventual firing. She also discusses her thirty year collaboration with Minutemen founder, Mike Watt. The interview also covers Roessler's current career as a dialogue editor.
  Kira Roessler (b. 1962) is a musician, bassist, singer, and Emmy award winning dialogue editor. She was the bass player for Black Flag from 1983-1985 and co-founded the two-bass duo, Dos, with Mike Watt from Minutemen. She currently resides in Los Angeles, CA and works as a dialogue editor on theatrical films.
  Roessler, Kira
  - Video interview of Kira Roessler
- Cynthia Ross interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2016 December 27; Ross, Cynthia; 1 oral histories (1 video)
  In this oral history, Cynthia Ross details her childhood and adolescence, growing up in Toronto. She discusses her artistic nature, relationship with her sisters and parents, particularly her mother. Ross talks about the music scene in Toronto, the formation of the B-Girls and eventual move to New York City. She discusses personal and professional relationships with punk icons, and how the B-Girls helped shape the New York scene with their unique sound. Ross details the B-Girls break up, motherhood, marriage, education, her careers, and passion for human rights and social justice.The interview concludes with her thoughts on aging, the history of women in rock and her return to New York to pursue music once again.
  Cynthia Ross is a bass player and founding member of the hugely influential punk band The B-Girls. She has shared the stage with Blondie, the B-52's, the Dead Boys and the Clash, among others. Ross has pursued several careers, always with a focus on social justice and human rights. She is a mother, a writer, an artist and currently plays bass in New York Junk.
  Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrator. An edited version of the video is available for research.
  Ross, Cynthia
  - Redacted video interview of Cynthia Ross
    Portions of this interview have been closed by the narrator. This edited version of the video is open for research.
- JD Samson interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 January 6; Samson, JD, 1978-; Pearson, Tanya; 1 oral histories (video and transcript)
  In this oral history JD Samson describes her upbringing and experiences as a gay teenager and activist in small town Ohio and the pivotal moment that fostered her interest in film and visual arts. She discusses her time in New York City at Sarah Lawrence College, her involvement in the local music scene and joining her first band, Le Tigre, with Riot Grrrl figurehead, Kathleen Hanna. Samson details her experience within the music business as a female identified "gender-outlaw" and how this experience diverges from the "women of rock" category.
  JD Samson (b. 1978) grew up in Pepper Pike Ohio where she came out as a lesbian at age 15. A visual artist, she went on to attend Sarah Lawrence College where she majored in experimental film and graduated in 2000. Samson joined electro-feminist band, Le Tigre with Kathleen Hanna and Johanna Fateman as projectionist, producer and then full-fledged band member. Samson founded DJ project MEN after Le Tigre disbanded and toured with Peaches and Gossip. She has a songwriting and publishing deal through Universal Music Publishing Group and has written songs for Christina Aguilera and Pussy Riot.
  Samson, JD, 1978-